歡迎大家來到我們的聖誕重拜
開始的時候我想和你分享一個小小的秘密
我小時候很不喜歡聖誕重禮
不是因為我不喜歡回教會
而是我覺得聖誕節回教會特別沒有意思
聖誕講道通常是特別軟熟的
可能是因為要迎合大眾的口味
而參加聚會的人
又好像特別不耐煩
唱完詩歌之後肚子開始餓
就在想以後一會兒吃什麼
根本無心去聽這篇道
那個不是一個真正的教會
那個不是一個真正的崇拜
那個更加不是一個真正的聖誕
那個不是一個真正的教會
那個不是一個真正的崇拜
所以今天我一反常態
我取消了聖誕大餐
說笑而已
食物還沒到
不過我確實是想講一篇很不入流的聖誕訊息
因為唯有這樣你才可以明白
發現聖誕的真意
發現聖誕的真相
我想帶你回到我們現在的世界
在普天同慶基督降臨的日子
我們應該如何佈置一間教會呢
我們用什麼顏色用什麼材料呢
一般來說現代人喜歡用紅色
聖誕花的顏色
綠色聖誕樹
金色銀色喜慶的顏色
但我不知道你有沒有想過
這些佈置和選材完全不配合聖誕的故事
沒辦法將聖誕的氣氛帶到我們教會裏面
在基督教會的傳統裏面
一踏入十二月
就是叫做將臨期就是耶穌將要臨到的時期
我們熱切期待耶穌的來臨
其實有兩重的意義
第一個就是我們等待耶穌第一次
二千多年前祂第一次的來臨
第二個意義是我們等待祂第二次
祂將要來臨
祂快要來臨
祂必要來臨
祂回來世上的降臨
所以開始的時候我們才時光倒流
二千多年
耶穌出生的時候
祂出生在馬槽裏面
馬槽的聖嬰世人的救主
如果我們要配合當時的聖誕氣氛
聖誕場景
基本上教會應該什麼都不做
最多是窗口貼幾隻大字就差不多了
這個是第一次的來臨
如果你想第二次的來臨
你現在向前張望耶穌再回來的日子
耶穌快要回來
耶穌必定回來
這個時候我們才時光倒流
這是聖經的教導
所以我今天講到的題目是
The Last Christmas
不是上個聖誕節
而是最後一個聖誕節
它也是人類歷史裏面的最後一天
最後一個聖誕將會是一個怎樣的日子呢
是不是還是普天同慶呢
不是
最後一個聖誕是一個上帝憤怒的日子
是上帝回來公義審判這個世界的日子
如果我們要配合那一天
最後一個聖誕那個氣氛的話
那就大災了
應該是火光熊熊
將教會弄到火光熊熊就對了
去到一個地步
街外的人見到我們十三樓的情況
應該會打999的
通過的地方會打999給火力部隊
最後的一個聖誕是人類歷史裏面最後的一天
是上帝審判的日子
火光熊熊
萬民哀號的日子
The Last Christmas is the last day of human history
It is a day of God's righteous judgment on mankind
It is a day of flames roaring and all people wailing
但大家記得每一年的聖誕
在教會的傳統裏面
我們不單止望後面
我們也望前面
我們等待著最後的一個聖誕的來臨
So every Christmas
Not only do we look backwards at Christ's first coming
We also look forward to Christ's second coming
所以如果你回到教會
你見到只有聖嬰那些 Nativity scene
其實是正確的一半
So if you go to church and you only see Nativity scene
You are only half correct
我們真正要想的是最後那一天
We need to think about the last day
當我們仰望最後一個聖誕
最後人類歷史的一天的時候
歷代的聖徒鼓勵我們要審慎思考四樣東西
So when we think about the last day
The saints throughout the ages encourage us to carefully contemplate four things
不是我作的
這是教會歷史裏面是前人鼓勵我們
在聖誕的時候要思想四樣
四樣終極的人生大事
I did not make this up
But it is the saints throughout the ages
Encourage us to think about four ultimate matters of life
他們說這四樣是最後的事 最終最後的事
So these four things are the ultimate are the last things
按照傳統的次序就是死亡 審判 天堂 地獄
So according to the traditional order
They are death, judgment, heaven and hell
他們是基督教會在聖誕時候默想的四大焦點
They are what the Christian church would meditate upon during Christmas
這樣都可以? How can it be?
有點消極
Isn't it a bit negative?
我們現在喜慶的日子
Isn't it a joyful season?
應該往前看 明天會更好
Shouldn't we be forward looking?
在這個時候全世界都是世界和平 豐衣足食 出入平安 身體健康
World peace, abundance, protection, good health
我今天抽時間來到你這間教會 你跟我說要生要死?
Today I take time to your church but you tell me about life and death?
為什麼要說要生要死?
Why do we talk about life and death?
其實很簡單
The reason is simple
因為你跟我遲到都會死
Because you and I will all die sooner or later
我們必定會死
We will definitely die
這個時候說要死其實是最正確的
It is right to talk about death now
每年到了這個時候
報紙 雜誌 網上平台都有很多大同小異的紀念活動
So every year during this time
You see from newspaper, magazines and online platforms
We see memorial activities
他說今年我們死了哪些我們最愛的人士
They say this year which people that we love died
有沒有留意到中間有年長的
Have you noticed that they are the younger ones
亦都有年輕的
They are the older ones
你估你下一年有沒有榜上有名
Do you think that you will be on the list next year?
就算你沒有
其實你跟我已經在排排坐
等待上帝金榜提名
Even if not, you and I are actually waiting
God to call upon your name
可能你會說死又如何呢
You might say, so what if I die?
平生不作虧心事
半夜敲門也不驚
I have a clear conscience
and I am not afraid of a door knock in the middle of the night
又或者你會說
我不信天堂地獄
我只信人死如燈滅
Or you would say, I don't believe in heaven and hell
I believe that when people die, that's all
又或者你說,我信輪迴再世
Or you say, I believe in reincarnation
下世再見
and we will meet again
甚至你可以很堅決告訴我
你是一個好人
You might even think that you are a good person
就算有天堂地獄
你只會上天堂,不會下地獄
So even if there is heaven and hell, you will go to heaven, not hell
我無法控制你的想法
It is not for me to control what you think
但我諗我哋每個人都需要接受一個溫馨提示
But I would like to gently remind you
每一個人諗嘅嘢只係你自己嘅想法
The thought of everyone is just his or her own belief
未必一定係真嘅
It may not be true
當你去返聖經上帝嘅話語嘅時候
Whereas when you go to the Bible, go to God's word
呢個係我哋基督徒所相信
唔單止係人寫嘅,而係上帝畀我哋嘅啟示
This is what we believe, it is not only written by human
but also the revelation from God
聖經話畀我哋知,畀我哋睇到一個好唔一樣嘅角度
The Bible offers us a very different perspective
聖經話當人跟隨咗亞當夏娃叛逆上帝
做自己眼中看為對嘅事嘅時候
So the Bible says when people follow their ancestors Adam and Eve
and they do what they see as right in their own eyes
我哋每個人都犯咗叛軍叛國嘅罪名
We all commit treason, we all commit the sin of rebellion against God
喺上帝面前
In the eyes of God
我哋每個人都係最大惡嘅
該下地獄嘅人
We are all great sinners deserving hell
喺人世間嘅社會裏面
In human society
你我身家清白
We might be innocent of a clean record
甚至我哋當中可能有啲人係滿有德行
Even some of us may be called virtuous people
呢個係因為當人叛逆咗上帝之後
你重新定義咩叫好咩叫壞
That is because after humanity's rebellion against God
Man redefined what is good and what is evil
你可以話有一班叛賊佢哋逃跑去另外一個對方
跟住佢哋改名換姓改頭換面
脫去以為咁樣就可以脫去佢哋嘅罪人嘅身份
佢哋該受嘅刑罰
You can imagine that it is like a rebellious army going to a new place
Change their name and identity
Thinking that this can help them to escape from justice
佢哋從來冇諗過
嗰個軍王會有一日捉返佢哋返去
佢哋仍然係罪人嘅身份
佢仍然會接受嗰個大軍王嘅刑罰
They have not thought that one day
The king will come back and catch them
And bring them to justice
The justice that they deserve
聖經話其實我哋每個人都知道我哋係罪人
The Bible says that everyone knows that he or she is a sinner
因為我哋每個人都會死
Because all of us will die
你死亡嘅原因唔係因為病
因為其他嘢
你最終極嘅死亡原因
係因為你係一個罪人
所以上帝嘅審判會臨到你
The ultimate reason for death
Is because of sin and judgement against sin
Will come upon sinners
聖經咁樣揭示我哋嘅真相
The Bible reveals us the truth this way
聖經話世人都犯了罪
規決了上帝的榮耀
The Bible says for all have sinned
And fall short of the glory of God
罪的公間乃是死
跟住死後且有審判
The wages of sin is death
And after death comes judgement
聖經揭示我哋聽我哋死前嘅真相
死亡嘅真相同埋死後嘅真相
The Bible reveals the truth before death
The truth of death
And the truth after death
死前我哋就係罪人
死係因為罪嘅緣故
死後除咗死亡之外
仲有終極嘅審判
The truth before death is that we are a sinner
And the truth of death is that it is because of sin
And the truth after death is that there will be judgement
耶穌嘅再嚟
The re-coming of Jesus
最後嘅聖誕
會將呢三重嘅真相
徹底嘅決中
The last Christmas will be the time
Where these three realities will be realized
上帝會將我哋一生嘅罪業
God will expose a whole lifetime of sin
等我哋無可推諉
So that we have no reason
And we have no excuse
我想帶你去睇後書第三章第十節
I want to show you 2 Peter chapter 3 verse 10
但主的日子最後嘅聖誕
要像賊一樣嚟到
那日天必轟然一星
仲笑實天體都要被烈火熔化
地和地上的萬物
包括你同我都要被暴露無遺
But the day of the Lord will come like a thief
Then the heavens will pass away with a roar
And the heavenly bodies will be burnt up and dissolved
And the earth and the works that are done on it
Will be exposed
主的日子像賊一樣係因為
意思係你同我無意料嘅時候
佢會降臨
Like a thief means that you and I
cannot predict the time that he comes
嚟嘅時候係轟然一星
呢個世界消失
予以烈火所熔化
代表咗上帝憤怒同審判
You see that the day will pass away with a roar
And the heavens will be dissolved with fire
representing God's wrath and judgment
跟住地上地上嘅萬物都要暴露無遺
And the earth and everything done in it will be exposed
如果你有機會去睇下中文聖經
有啲翻譯係都要被燒盡
Some translation will say will be burns up
我當時諗燒盡就好
我哋犯罪證據都冇曬
So I thought if burned up it is a good thing
但係正確嘅翻譯唔係燒盡而係暴露
並且係暴露無遺
However the correct translation is not burned up
but exposed and in fact completely exposed
或者你可以咁樣去想像
So you can imagine it this way
由你懷胎嘅嗰一刻開始
From your conception
去到而家去到將來
Until now and into the future
上帝冇錯過你生命裏面嘅任何一個片段
God has not missed out any moment
你每段嘅人生
你每個思想
你每個行為
你所做過嘅嘢
你所諗過嘅嘢
上帝全部有天眼有心眼錄咗落嚟
So every moment of your life
Every thought
Every action
Everything your body has done
And everything your heart has thought
They are all recorded by God
然後喺最後嘅聖誕
終極嘅審判中暴露無遺
Then all these will be completely exposed
in the last Christmas
The ultimate judgment
天網恢恢 疏而不漏
善有善報 惡有惡報
若然未報 皆因時辰未到
And they say as in the Chinese idiom
The net of heaven lets nothing through
And good begets good
Evil begets evil
In fact if not yet repaid
It is just because the time has not yet come
唔係講緊啲大壞蛋
係講緊你同我
We are not talking about the villains
We are talking about you and me
但時候終於會到
就係嗰日最後嘅聖誕終極嘅審判
所有我哋嘅罪行
我哋嘅罪念
全部會暴露出嚟
But the time has finally come
And on that day, the last Christmas
All will be exposed
Our sin, our sinful thoughts
Our sinful desires
於是我哋從終極嘅審判
最後嘅聖誕
帶你進入上帝永遠嘅刑罰
So we go from the last Christmas
To the ultimate judgment
貼曬來家後書
聖經嘅另外一本書裏面
第一章我想讀啲三字俾你聽
So let me read from you
Another book in the Bible
2nd Thessalonians chapter 1 verse 7 to 9
那時最後嘅聖誕
耶穌同佢有能力的天使
從天上在火焰中顯現
要報應那不認識上帝
不聽從我主耶穌基督福音的人
佢們要受刑罰
就是永遠沉淪
離開主的面
他權能的榮光
So the Lord Jesus is revealed from the heaven
With his mighty angels in flaming fire
Infecting vengeance on those who do not know God
And on those who do not obey the gospel of our Lord Jesus
呢度講上帝嘅刑罰
會臨到嗰啲不認識上帝
其實個原文
另外一個翻譯更好嘅翻譯
係不愛慕上帝嘅人
So it is said here
That vengeance will come upon those who do not know God
But in fact the correct translation
Should be on those who do not love God
同埋嗰啲聽了福音
但係冇聽從福音嘅人
And also those who have heard the gospel
But refuse to obey the gospel
咁咪大祭啦你
你今日聽咗福音
但係你唔係聽唔聽到福音嘅問題
係聽唔聽從福音嘅問題
The essence is not whether you have heard the gospel
The essence is that whether you choose to believe
And obey the gospel
聖經話我哋唔迴轉
唔信靠
唔跟隨上帝嘅時候
我哋會進入永遠嘅沉淪
代表緊嘅係地獄
And the Bible says that if we refuse to obey and repent
Eternal destruction here means hell
乜嘢係地獄
What is hell
進入地獄一方面係離開主嘅面同埋主嘅榮光
就係上帝一切嘅美善
一切嘅慈愛信誓
So on the one hand hell is departure
From the presence and glory of God
And all his kindness and faithfulness
另一方面進入地獄就係進入上帝永恆嘅憤怒之中
And on the other hand entering hell
Is also entering into God's eternal wrath
於是死亡 審判 天堂 地獄
呢個係我哋等待最後聖誕
應該思想嘅四件終極大事
So death, judgment, heaven, hell
These are the four things to ponder as we wait for the last Christmas
不過我懇求大家唔好諗咁多天堂
But I implore everyone don't think too much about heaven
未必同你有關嘅
It may not be relevant to you
我反而鼓勵大家多反思地獄
But rather I would encourage you to reflect more on hell
去思想地獄嘅真實
To reflect upon the reality of hell
去思想你自己就在其中
And to imagine that you were there
我想同你分享一個兩分鐘嘅一個宣講
I want to share with you a two-minute sermon
呢兩分鐘係我以前嘅神學院嘅老師所錄製嘅
Which was recorded by one of my seminary professors
咁佢係一個幾有名嘅神學家
佢個名叫Sinclair Ferguson
He is quite a well-known theologian called Sinclair Ferguson
個題目係The Reality of Hell 地獄嘅真實
And the title Reality of Hell
呢個錄音分為三段 每段真係三十秒
I've divided his recording into three sections
Each 30 seconds long
咁我每段我播畀大家聽
我又預備咗有中英文嘅字幕
And have prepared subtitles in both Chinese and English
但係大家真係要留心聽
I want you to pay attention
OK 我諗應該夠大聲㗎啦
People sometimes say that we don't know much about heaven
But that's not strictly true
We haven't experienced much of it for sure
But the Bible has a lot to say about it
We could say we know even less about hell
Which is true
Nevertheless the Bible does have quite a lot to say about it
And it's often said with some degree of truth
That Jesus spoke more often about it than anyone else in the Bible
The fact that our loving Lord Jesus did so
Is a very sobering fact about a very sobering truth
But he said it because he loves us
或者我可以讀返個中文少少
人們有時說
我們不知道很多關於天堂的事
但嚴格來說者並不完全正確
佢講緊係你讀聖經嘅時候
你會知道天堂係啲乜嘢嘢
對於天堂我們沒有經驗那是一定的
即係話我哋知道有一啲嘢
但係我哋唔知道天堂究竟係因為我哋從來未經歷過
但聖經說了很多
我們可以說對於地獄我們知道的更少
這也是真的
儘管如此
聖經確實對地獄有很多的論說
且有人常說
耶穌談論地獄比聖經中任何人都多
這說法也有一定的道理
跟住佢總結
我們慈愛的主耶穌基督這樣談論地獄
是個嚴肅的事
關乎一個嚴肅的真理
是因為祂愛我們
我想用三點幫大家總結這三十秒
I want to use 3 points to summarize these 30 seconds
聖經對地獄有很多的論說
First of all, the Bible has a lot to say about hell
第二,耶穌談論地獄比聖經中任何人都更多
Second, Jesus talked about hell more than anyone else in the Bible
但最重要的是
耶穌談論地獄是因為祂愛我們
But most importantly, Jesus talked about hell because He loved us
延伸到我們今天
So extending this to us
十教基督教會全體同人心愛大家
Everyone at cross way also deeply loves one another
因此他們在聖誕崇拜裏面指派我向你們宣講地獄
For that reason, for this Christmas worship, they want me to talk about hell
不是咒你
It is not to curse you
是因為愛你
But because they love you
不想你跌入地獄裏面
They don't want you to fall into hell
好,第二段
I once heard a story
A member of the British royal family asked a member of the clergy of the Church of England
If there was a hell
And the clergyman apparently replied
Your Highness, the Bible says so
Jesus taught so
And the articles of the Church of England affirm so
To which the member of the royal family was reported to respond
Then why in God's name do you not tell us about it?
我老師是一個蘇格蘭人
是一個英聯邦裏面的人
So my teacher was a Scottish
Which was part of Great Britain
所以他會經常講一些故事是關於英國皇室的
So he would tell a lot of stories about the British royal family
這是一個很有趣的故事
It is an interesting story
他說我曾經聽過一個故事
有一位英國皇室的成員
可能他聖誕節崇拜園
或者是復活節還是什麼
向一個聖公會
香港有很多聖公會的學校
大家知道的
Church of England
向一個聖公會的神職人員詢問
他說到底有沒有地獄
這個神職人員這樣回答
他說,殿下,聖經說有的
耶穌也說有的
我們聖公會的信仰告白
也都認定是有的
接著這個皇室成員就回答
那為什麼你不清清楚楚告訴我們是有的
你開始明白其實教會
已經是開始不講地獄了
So you start to realize
that the teaching of hell
is fading in the church
但是這個哀吆的
返教會的皇室人員
都開始明白那個嚴重性
But this member of the royal family
who attend church
start to see the gravity of the problem
我又用三點去總結
I use three points to summarize
聖經多方教導地獄的真實
The Bible teaches extensively about the reality of hell
你可以不相信
但是聖經多方教導地獄的真實是真的
You are at liberty not to believe in it
But the Bible teaches the reality of hell
耶穌親口宣講地獄的真實
Jesus personally preach about the reality of hell
歷代教會也都認定地獄的真實
And throughout history the church has also affirmed
the reality of hell
所以你說我怎敢不告訴大家
不警告大家地獄的真實呢
Therefore how could I not tell and not warn you
about the reality of hell
第三段 最後一段
The third section, the final section
我想你留心聽Ferguson怎麼說
Please listen carefully to Sinclair Ferguson
But what is hell
The Bible doesn't try to answer that question
in subtle philosophical terms
Rather it paints pictures
because its basic concern
is to tell us how to avoid it
and it tells us why we need to avoid it
because it means to be separated
from all the privileges and blessings
not only of God's saving grace
but of God's common grace
and what that means
can't fully be described in terms we can understand
It's too awful to understand
最後三點總結
So three summary points
第一
First
聖經繪畫了很多圖畫
來幫助我們感受到地獄難以理解的可怕
The Bible paints many pictures
to help us grasp the incomprehensible horror of hell
為什麼
因為它想你逃離地獄
Why it is to urge us to escape hell
第二
地獄意味著我們將與一切
好處和福氣分離
Hell means being separated from all goodness and blessings
不單止是上帝救贖的恩典
所謂這個救贖恩典就是天堂的意思
Not only God's saving grace meaning going to heaven
還包括地獄是告訴我們
我們再沒有上帝的普遍恩典
But hell also means that we no longer has God's common grace
當我聽到這一段的時候
其實我心裏面非常驚恐
When I heard this section I was deeply terrified
因為我都讀過一下神學
Because I also studied some theology
我知道什麼叫普遍恩典
它說地獄不單止是沒有了上帝永恆的救贖
即是天堂
亦都是告訴我們當地獄來到的時候
當我們進入地獄的時候
我們連上帝普遍的恩典都沒有了
And I know something about common grace
And Sinclair Ferguson said that
Hell not only means that we do not have God's saving grace
But also His common grace
我為我很多不愛慕上帝
不停從上帝的親戚朋友擔憂
I'm concerned for many of my relatives and friends
who do not love God and do not obey God
大家聽一下地獄意味著我們失去上帝的普遍恩典
So pay attention
Hell means that we are separated
And we lose the common grace of God
就是說我們再沒有一個保護罩
時間亦都不會再拖延
而是我們直接被上帝拉進他永恆的怒火當中
So it means that we no longer have protection
And there will be no more delays
We are being immediately cast into God's fierce wrath
是什麼意思呢 我都聽不明白
What does it mean? I don't understand
我給個比喻你
Let me give you an analogy
我曾經看過一套美國的電視劇
So I once watched an American TV series
在劇中有個警探的太太
她被一個罪犯用炸彈炸死了
So in that series
A detective's wife was killed by a bomb planted by a criminal
經過很多年的努力
這個警探終於找到那個兇手
After many years, the detective finally found the culprit who killed his wife
但當他找到這個兇手的時候
他已經是末期癌症
臥床不起 在醫院剩下幾天命
But by that time, the culprit was already terminally ill
He's left with a few days to live
這個警探就去到醫院的房間
和這個兇手談了幾句
So the detective went into the hospital room and said a few words
他也承認了他自己的罪行
And the murderer also confessed his sin
但又怎樣呢 他就快死了嘛
And so what? He was going to die very soon
他在床上仍然舒舒服服
He was still comfortable on bed
接著這個警探要離開房間的時候
So as the detective was going to leave the room
他將連著在這個犯人手的馬菲基關掉
He turned off the morphing machine that was attached to the murderer
你明白嗎 那個人為什麼可以這麼舒服和你聊天
Do you understand why could that man be talking to the detective so comfortably
因為有個馬菲基
Because there was a morphing machine
幾秒鐘之後這個罪犯開始感到異常的疼痛
A few seconds later, the murderer began to feel extreme pain
我想你記住這幅圖
I want you to remember this picture
很多時候我們向上帝埋怨
Many times we complain to God
我說這個世界有多少苦難
太痛苦 太難受
We complain about this world being full of suffering
Too painful, too hard
我們從來沒有想過
現在的世界 墮落之後的世界
其實在馬菲基的供應之下
We never thought about nor understood
That this present world and the fallen world
Is in fact under the supply of a morphing machine
我們是一個墮落之後的世界
我們是一個應該受上帝刑罰的世界
We are in a fallen world
And we are in a world that deserves God's judgment
然而上帝給了我們一個普遍恩典的保護罩
But God has given us a common grace, a protective shield
令到我們在地上所接受的痛苦
是得以減少
So as to mitigate the suffering that we feel now
甚至是大大的減少
And in fact, it is a great deal of mitigation
但是有一天
But one day
普遍恩典的保護罩不會再保護你
The protective shield of common grace
Will no longer protect humanity
上帝的烈怒會全面的降臨在你身上
God's fierce wrath will be fully unleashed onto you and me
你知道我做牧師
有時候去探那些快要不行的病人的時候
心裏面是很忐忑的
So as a pastor
Whenever I go to visit people whose life is going to end very soon
I have this great limer in my heart
因為尤其是那一人不信主
Especially when that person do not believe in God
家人可能去到最後那一步
說他那麼辛苦讓他走
His friends and family may be saying that
He is suffering, let him go
然後他就會安靜下來
不用再痛苦
So that he could rest in peace
There will be no more suffering
但因為我是一個基督徒
But because I am a Christian
我知道那個所謂讓他走
其實是將他送去一個再沒有普遍恩典的世界裏面
I know that so-called let him go
Is to release him into a world
Where there is no longer common grace
就這樣看
那個人好像安靜了下來
On the face of it
The person seems to be resting in peace
但實際上這個人進入了另外一個史無前例的恐怖世界
But in reality, the man has passed into a world
That is unprecedentedly horrifying
我回到他這第三段的總結
I go to summarize this section
聖經繪畫了很多圖畫關於地獄的
令我們可以感受到那種難以理解的可怕
以至我們可以逃避地獄
The Bible paints many pictures
To help us grasp the incomprehensible horror of hell
Urging us to escape from it
Ferguson第二個point說
地獄不單止是我們去不到天堂享受上帝
而是連上帝現在給我們的保護罩都要拿去
The second point is that
Hell not only means that
We are not able to enjoy God in heaven
But also means the taking away of our protective shield
總之還有第三個point
But thank God there is still the third point
第三個point是聖經亦都同時告訴我們
如何可以逃離地獄
The third point is that
The Bible does tell us how to escape from it
如何
簡單來說是在耶穌基督裡
Simply put it is in Jesus Christ
當我們打開新約聖經的時候
我們見到這個馬槽的聖嬰
要長大成人成為十字架上的救主
So when we open the Bible
We see that holy infant in the manger
Would grow up to be a savior
所以你看聖經不要只看前面
即是看福音書兩章三章
耶穌出世很可愛
根本就不是那個point
The point is at the end
這個馬槽的嬰孩要成為十字架上的救主
如果不是聖誕節又有什麼意義呢
So the point is not at the birth of Jesus Christ
But at the end
Otherwise Christmas has no real significance
於是馬開福音
在耶穌被釘十字架的時候
耶穌大聲呼喊
我的上帝 我的上帝
為何要離棄我
So in the Gothel of Mark
When Jesus was on the cross
Jesus cried with a loud voice
耶穌為了跟隨祂的人
去經歷地獄
Jesus experienced death
For those who follow Him
司徒保羅在哥倫多後書
第五章裡面這樣去解釋
耶穌的死
So the Apostle Paul explained
Jesus' death in 2 Corinthians this way
他說 上帝使那無罪的耶穌
替我們成為罪
好使我們在他裡面成為上帝的兒
So for our sake
He made Him to be seen
Who knew no sin
So that in Him
We might become the righteousness of God
聖經告訴我們
我們這裡每一個人都極其需要耶穌
So the Bible says
That every one of us here
Desperately need Jesus
我們不是偶然需要耶穌
不是我們病的時候
有困難的時候需要耶穌
我們是極其每一刻需要耶穌
So not that we just need Jesus
Sometime
But we need Jesus at all times
我們需要祂的誕生
我們需要祂的壽死
我們需要祂的復活
So we need His Christmas
We need His Good Friday
And we need His Resurrection
因為世人都犯了罪
犯了上帝的榮耀
罪的公間乃是死
死後且有終極的審判
Because we have all sins
And foreshort of the glory of God
The wages of sin is death
And after death comes the ultimate judgment
你信不信呢
Do you believe in it
如果今天你在街上
突然間遇到一個算命先生
So imagine today
You are walking on the street
And suddenly
You come across a fortune teller
跟住算命先生同你講
先生小姐
請恕我直言
我睇到你印堂發黑
目光呆滯
我好驚你好快就大過我臨頭
So the fortune teller said
Sir, Madam
Please forgive my bluntness
But I see that your forehead is dark
And your eyes are dull
I fear that you will encounter
Great misfortune very soon
你會有咩反應呢
How would you react
我相信係香港唔少嘅
香港人都會咁回應
I believe many people in Hong Kong
would respond in this way
阿師傅請你高人指點
有咩化解嘅方法
So master, master
Please guide me
Is there a way to resolve it
但如果呢個人唔係算命先生
而係教會牧師
But what if this person
is not a fortune teller
but a pastor
更有可能嘅回應係
喂你邊位呀白狀呀
Your likely response would be
Who are you, crazy, absurd
就算係咁樣
我都仲要同你講埋最後嗰句
However, I still have to tell you
One last time
你真係目光呆滯
人頭發黑
天火籠罩隨時爆發
你相唔相信
You really have dull eyes
And a dark forehead
The heavenly fire is looming over you
Ready to be unleashed anytime
Do you believe in it
你唔需要信我
You don't have to believe me
但你需要信上帝
But you should believe in God's word
上帝嘅話語
In the word of God
我哋係祈禱
Let's pray together
我哋天父我哋多謝你
畀我哋聖誕
Our Father in heaven
We thank you for giving us Christmas
我哋多謝你
你唔單止畀我哋第一個聖誕
你亦都畀我哋第二個聖誕
Not only do you give us
The first Christmas
But also the second Christmas
但我哋講完之後
我哋要將佢調返轉嚟講
我哋多謝你
畀我哋最後一個聖誕
但我哋更多謝你
畀我哋第一個聖誕
And in fact the other way round is true
We thank you giving us
The second Christmas
But because also
You also gave us
The first Christmas
如果冇咗第一個聖誕
第二個聖誕
對於我哋所有嘅人
都係極其恐怖嘅日子
If the first Christmas
Did not exist
Then the second Christmas
would be a horrible day for all of us
我求主你幫助我哋呢度
每一個都有機會聽到嘅人
去思想聖誕與我哋嘅關係
I pray that all of us here
who are listening to the sermon
would reflect upon the meaning
of Christmas in our lives
因為我哋呢個世界
充滿住好多無知嘅人
佢哋盲目嘅去慶祝聖誕
Because there are far too many
ignorant people now
celebrating Christmas without knowing
有一日最後聖誕離臨嘅時候
One day when the last Christmas comes
佢哋會發現
佢哋冇辦法再慶祝
They will discover that
there is no way for them to celebrate
佢哋嘅一生會
喺上帝面前被暴露無遺
The whole life will be exposed
in front of God
證據確鑿
The evidence are sure
被判永遠嘅沉淪
Being sentenced to eternal hell
讓你嘅普遍恩典
從此不再保護佢哋
And your common craze
will no longer protect them
呢個係一個
好極何其恐怖嘅事情
How horrible and terrifying this is
我哋求主你讓我哋做聰明明智嘅人
We pray that you will make us
into wise people
當我哋趁住我哋仲有命嘅時候
去思想終極嘅事情
As we still have time on earth
let us think about the ultimate things
尤其是喺聖誕嘅時候
思想死亡
思想審判
思想天堂
思想地獄
Especially in Christmas
let us think about death
let us think about judgment
let us think about heaven and hell
當然
讓我哋思想耶穌基督
Let us think about Jesus Christ
並佢嘅十字架
And his cross
多謝你
Thank you Lord
與我哋呢度每一位朋友
家人同一齊
That we are being able to be
with our friends and families here
希望佢哋唔需要
等到下一年嘅聖誕再返嚟
Hope that we do not need to wait
until the next Christmas that they come back
而係喺新年裏面立志
打開哋本聖經
去思想人生嘅終極
But in this new year
may we resolve to open the Bible
to read it
and to think about
the ultimate things of life
我哋咁樣祈禱係奉主耶穌基督名求
And we pray this
in the name of Jesus Christ
Amen